眼見並不為實
Seeing is not believing.
我們的感官會誤導我們
Our senses can deceive us.
這些星星並不是我們看到的樣子
Even the stars are not what they appear to be.
通過科學展示出的宇宙
The cosmos, as revealed by science,
比我們所能想像的更離奇
is stranger than we ever could have imagined.
光 時間 空間 萬有引力
Light and time and space and gravity
共同創造出
conspire to create realities
我們從未體驗過的現實
which lie beyond human experience.
讓我們一探究竟
That's where we're headed.
跟我來
Come with me.
1802年 像這樣的一個夜晚
Back in 1802, on a night like this,
天文學家威廉·赫歇爾和他的兒子
the astronomer William Herschel strolled the beach
在英國海邊散步
on the English coast, with his son John.
赫歇爾是有史以來第一位
Herschel was the first person ever
恆星天文學之父
看穿宇宙深層奧秘的人
to see into the deeper waters of the cosmic ocean.
他看穿了光線和時間
There he glimpsed the magic trick
一起變出的戲法
that light does with time.
父親
Father...
你相信有鬼魂嗎
do you believe in ghosts?
怎麼了  我相信
Why, yes, my son!
你信
You, you do?
我真沒想到
I would not have thought so.
不是人死後的鬼魂
Oh, no, not in the human kind of ghost.
絕不是那種
No... not at all.
抬頭看 兒子
But look up, my boy,
天空中滿是鬼魂
and see a sky full of them.
星星  父親
The stars, Father?
我沒聽懂
I do not follow.
每個星星都像我們的太陽那麼亮 那麼大
Every star is a sun as big, as bright as our own.
想想看要把太陽移到多遠以外
Just imagine how far away from us you'd have to move the Sun
才能讓它看上去像星星那樣小
to make it appear as small and faint as a star.
星星發出的光 速度很快
The light from the stars travels very fast...
最快的速度
faster than anything...
但並不是無限的快
but not infinitely fast.
星光到達我們這裏需要時間
It takes time for their light to reach us.
最近的可能需要幾年
For the nearest ones, it takes years.
其他那些  幾百年
For others, centuries.
還有一些特別遠的
Some stars are so far away,
需要億萬年才能到達地球
it takes eons for their light to get to Earth.
等那些星星發出的光到達這裏
By the time the light from some stars gets here,
星星已經死了
they are already dead.
對這些星星來說  我們看到的只是他們的鬼魂
For those stars, we see only their ghosts.
我們看到他們的光
We see their light,
但他們的星球已經死了很久很久
but their bodies perished long, long ago.
約翰  我比我們的古人
John, I have seen further back in time
能看到更古老的過去
than any man before me--
幾百萬年前的過去
millions of years into the past.
威廉·赫歇爾是第一個認識到
William Herschel was the first person to understand
望遠鏡就是一個時間機器
that a telescope is a time machine.
我們看向太空
We cannot look out into space
就是看向過去
without seeing back in time.
一秒鐘  光穿越30萬公里
In one second, light travels 300,000 kilometers,
或者18萬6千英里
or 186,000 miles.
幾乎就是地球到月亮的距離
That's nearly the distance from the Earth to the Moon.
所以月亮離我們1光秒
So, the Moon is about one light-second away.
下次你看向月亮
The next time you look at the Moon,
你就會看到1秒鐘以前的過去
you'll be seeing one second into the past.
中文翻譯：@SaltyEggPain
藍光版字幕製作  timhal@HDWinG字幕組
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息
宇宙大探索
第四集
太陽
That Sun...
並不真的在那個位置
it's not really there.
太陽實際上升出地平線
It won't actually be above the horizon
是兩分鐘以後的事情
for another two minutes.
日出只是個幻象
The sunrise is an illusion.
大氣層使射入的陽光發生了折射
Earth's atmosphere bends the incoming rays of sunlight
就像鏡片和一杯水那樣
like a lens or a glass of water.
所以我們看到的只是地平線之上的投影
So we see the image of the Sun projected above the horizon...
太陽本身還沒到達那個位置
before the physical Sun is actually there.
我身後的太陽只是海市蜃樓
That Sun behind me is a mirage.
就像那閃爍的圖像
No more real than the shimmering image
漂浮在
that hovers in the distance
炎熱天氣下的沙漠遠方
over a desert road on a hot day.
日光需要8分鐘才能達到地球
Sunlight takes about eight minutes to reach Earth,
太陽離我們8光分
so the Sun is eight light-minutes away.
對於太陽來說  我們只能看到它
From Earth, we can only ever see the Sun
8分鐘之前的樣子
as it was eight minutes ago.
還有一件事
And another thing,
太陽並不是真的 升起
the Sun doesn't really "rise" at all.
地球帶著我們一起旋轉
The Earth turns and we turn with it.
看上去也許不像  但是這個時候
It may not look like it, but right at this moment,
我比飛機走的還快
I'm moving faster than a jet plane
你也是  其他所有人都一樣
and so are you and everyone on Earth.
當我看過去
While I'm at it,
地平線
that horizon...
並不真的存在
it's not really there at all.
根本沒有邊緣
There's no edge.
地平線也只是一種幻象
The horizon is just another illusion.
地球離最外圍的行星
The distance between Earth
海王星的距離
and the outermost planet Neptune
隨著環日軌道而不同
varies as the planets orbit the Sun.
平均來說  光要4個小時才能傳來
On average, the light makes that trip in four hours.
所以對我們來說
So for us on Earth,
我們看到的是4小時前海王星的樣子
the Neptune we see is always four hours in the past--
距離 4光時
four light-hours away.
但行星間的距離
But the distances to the planets,
就算最遙遠的
even the farthest one...
相對星系間和恆星間的距離來說
are mere baby steps on a much grander scale
也只不過是微不足道的
of the stars and galaxies.
一旦我們離開太陽系
As soon as we leave the Sun's immediate neighborhood,
我們就需要把距離單位
we need to change the unitive distance
從光時換到光年
from light-hours to light-years.
光年是宇宙中的距離單位
A light-year is the yardstick of the cosmos.
1光年將近10萬億公里
A single one is nearly ten trillion kilometers,
大約6萬億英里
or about six trillion miles.
宇宙距離單位中  就像1米或1英里那樣
It's a unitive distance, just like a meter or a mile.
它是光線用1年時間可以穿越的距離長度
It's the distance light travels in a year.
離太陽最近的恆星  比鄰星
The nearest star to the Sun, Proxima Centauri,
由天文學家羅伯特·因尼斯於1915年在南非發現
離地球的距離超過4光年一點點
is a little more than four light-years away from Earth.
4光年有多遠
How far away is four light-years?
NASA的旅行者探測器
NASA's Voyager spacecraft moves
速度超過每小時5萬6千公里
at more than 56,000 kilometers an hour.
就算這麼驚人的速度
Even at that astonishing speed, it would take Voyager
也需要超過8萬年  才能到達最近的恆星
more than 80,000 years to reach the nearest star.
昂宿星團的恆星
And the stars of the Pleiades cluster,
一個大而明亮的疏散星團，位於金牛座，裸眼就可以輕易的看見
距離我們 400光年
400 light-years away.
想像之舟
The Ship of the Imagination
有著一種不同尋常的能力
is equipped with a highly unusual capability--
獨一無二的
one-of-a-kind, actually.
它能讓我們看到
It makes it possible for us to see what was happening
光從遙遠的恆星或星系發出
when the light from a distant star or galaxy first set out
直到地球的情形
on its long journey to Earth.
400年前  光從昴宿星團出發時
When that light left the Pleiades, about 400 years ago,
伽利略第一次使用望遠鏡
Galileo was taking his first look through a telescope.
幾年後 他嘗試測算光的速度
A few years later, he tried to measure the speed of light,
讓甲乙兩人在夜裏相隔一段距離面對面站著，每人都拿一盞提燈。
甲首先開燈，乙一看到甲的燈光立刻打開自己的燈。
但是沒有成功
but he couldn't do it.
他的計劃很高明  可惜當時的科技
He had a very clever plan, but the technology of that era
甲記下從自己開燈起到看到乙的燈光為止所經過的時間。
然後用甲乙之間距離的兩倍去除以這個時間，就得到光的速度。
還不能測量那麼快的速度
just wasn't good enough to measure the motion of anything
像光那麼快的速度
that moves as fast as light.
我們從地球上觀察蟹狀星雲時
When we look at the Crab Nebula from Earth,
我們看到的是更古老的過去
we're seeing much farther back in time.
蟹狀星雲曾是一顆巨大的恆星
The Crab Nebula was once a giant star,
質量比太陽大10倍
ten times the mass of the Sun,
爆炸成為一顆超新星
until it exploded in a supernova.
它的中心是顆脈衝星
At its heart is a pulsar,
城市般大小的一顆坍塌星
a collapsed star the size of a city,
中子星
每秒自轉30次
spinning 30 times a second.
脈衝星的螺旋磁場
This pulsar's whirling magnetic field
瘋狂地捲動 周圍的電子
whips nearby electrons into a frenzy,
將他們加速到接近光的速度
accelerating them to almost the speed of light.
他們發出藍色的光芒照亮超新星爆炸時
They shine with a blue glow that lights up the tendrils of gas
產生的氣態捲鬚
still unraveling from the supernova.
蟹狀星雲
The Crab Nebula
距離地球大約6500光年
is about 6,500 light-years from Earth.
在某些宗教信仰中
According to some beliefs,
那是整個宇宙的年紀
that's the age of the whole universe.
但如果宇宙只有6500歲
But if the universe were only 6,500 years old,
我們怎麼可能看到更遠的光
how could we see the light from anything more distant
比蟹狀星雲還遠的光
than the Crab Nebula?
做不到
We couldn't.
那並沒有足夠的時間
There wouldn't have been enough time for the light
讓光從距離超過6500光年的地方
to get to Earth from anywhere farther away
傳來地球
than 6,500 light-years in any direction.
那點時間只夠光在
That's just enough time for light to travel
我們的銀河系中穿越很短的距離
through a tiny portion of our Milky Way galaxy.
如果相信宇宙
To believe in a universe
只有6千到7千歲
as young as 6,000 or 7,000 years old
就是熄滅了銀河系中大部分的光
is to extinguish the light from most of the galaxy,
更別提那些可觀測宇宙中
not to mention the light from all the 100 billion
上千億星系發出的光
other galaxies in the observable universe.
我們銀河系的中心
The center of our own galaxy
距離地球大約3萬光年
is about 30,000 light-years from Earth.
我們今天看到的光
The light we see today
從銀河系的核心出發時
coming from the core of the Milky Way left there...
我們的遠古祖先找到了
when our ancestors were perfecting a way
超越死亡的方法
to vanquish death...
使用繪畫的力量
by making art with the power
給予後世啟示
to inspire those who would come long after they were gone.
從闊邊帽星系傳來的光
The light we see coming from the Sombrero Galaxy
其擁有明亮且巨大的星系核
尤其在赤道方向有一條由星際塵埃所形成的暗帶
是攝影愛好者的必定拍攝對像之一
走了3千萬年
is 30 million years old.
當光發出來時  我們的祖先還住在樹上
Our ancestors were living in trees when that light started out.
他們大約5公斤重  還有長長的尾巴
They weighed about five kilos and had long tails.
但就算離我們3千萬光年之外
But even 30 million light-years away
從宇宙中看 也不過就在我們的後院
is still in our own cosmic backyard.
那個星系屬於後發座星系團
That galaxy is part of the Coma Cluster,
3億2千萬光年之遙
320 million light-years away.
當這裏的光出發時
What was going on back home
當時的地球又是怎樣的呢
when the light you are seeing began its trip to Earth?
沒有我們熟悉的大陸  海洋  河流
No familiar continents, oceans or rivers.
我們的遠古祖先剛剛從水中登上陸地
Our distant ancestors were just leaving the water for the land.
很古老的光
That's pretty old light,
但遠不是 我們能看到的 最古老的光
but not nearly the oldest light we can see.
最古老的光已經很微弱了
The oldest light is very faint,
暗夜中虛弱的鬼魂
a pale ghost in the night.
看到圓圈中的紅點嗎
See that red blob inside the circle?
那是我們能見的最古老星系之一
That's one of the oldest galaxies we've ever seen.
你看到的是134億歲高齡的星光
You're looking at 13.4-billion year-old starlight
通過哈勃太空望遠鏡捕捉到的
as captured by the Hubble space telescope.
它來自第一代的星星
It's coming from the very first generation of stars.
當時的地球什麼情況
What was happening on Earth back then?
完全沒情況
Absolutely nothing.
當時 沒有地球 沒有太陽 沒有銀河系
There was no Earth, no Sun, no Milky Way.
它們都是幾十億年後才誕生的
They would not come to be for billions of years.
當我們看向宇宙的更深處
When we try to look even farther into the universe,
好像已經到了宇宙的盡頭
we come to what appears to be the end of space...
但事實上
but actually...
這是時間的開始
it's the beginning of time.
地球向下拉著我們
Earth pulls on us.
我們不斷地反抗引力
Our lives are a relentless struggle with gravity.
這個小女孩用盡全力要爬出
That little girl is trying her best to climb out
引力的包圍
of a gravitational well.
從第一次嘗試站立到最後的倒下
From our first efforts to stand to our final surrender,
我們一直在努力克服地心引力
we are struggling to overcome the Earth's pull.
我們在重力場中誕生  生活  過世
We are born, live and die in a force field--
重力場幾乎和宇宙本身一樣的古老
one that is almost as old as the universe itself.
有多古老
And how old is that?
為了想像宇宙的138億年歲月
To visualize the 13.8 billion year age of the universe,
我們把所有的宇宙時間
we've compressed all of cosmic time
壓縮在一份單張的年歷中
into a single year-at-a-glance calendar.
現在是12月31號的午夜
Midnight on December 31 is this very moment right now.
而1月1號就是時間的開始
And January 1 is the beginning of time.
看到那耀眼的煙霧嗎
See that glowing fog out there?
它是大爆炸遺留下的輻射物
It's radiation left over from the Big Bang,
在138億年前
the explosion that made the universe
大爆炸創造了宇宙
13.8 billion years ago.
現在 我們站在已知空間和時間的邊緣
Right now, we're at the very edge of known space and time.
那麼 大爆炸之前是什麼樣子呢
So what happened before the Big Bang?
沒人知道
Nobody knows.
沒有絲毫關於那之前的證據
No evidence survives from before that moment.
我們有一些很瘋狂的猜想
We've got some pretty crazy ideas
是關於宇宙的來源
about where the universe came from,
我們以後會提到
which we'll get to, in time.
我們在宇宙的什麼位置
Where are we in the universe?
就在正中心
At the very center.
在已知宇宙中 每個人都覺得自己很特殊
In the observed universe, everyone gets to feel special.
不論你身處哪個星系
No matter which galaxy you happen to live in,
當你看向宇宙時  你會發現自己
when you look out to the universe, you'll find yourself
身處宇宙地平線的中心
at the center of the cosmic horizon.
但這不過是個錯覺
But this is just an illusion.
實際上  沒有中心
In reality, there is no center,
宇宙地平線和海上的地平線 一樣不真實
and the cosmic horizon is no more real than the horizon at sea.
這是因為 在有起始時間的宇宙中
It's what you get when you have a finite speed of light
光速是有限的
in a universe that had a beginning in time.
大爆炸後的幾億年
A few hundred million years after the Big Bang,
大量的氫氣和氦氣雲團
vast clouds of hydrogen and helium condensed
凝結成最初的恆星和星系
into the first stars and galaxies.
有了這些新的光源
With these new sources of light,
宇宙漫長的黑暗時代從此終結
the long dark ages of the universe ended.
隨著宇宙的不斷膨脹
As space continued to expand,
宇宙進化的規模變得更加宏大
cosmic evolution unfolded on grander scales.
最初的星星死亡
As the first generation of stars died,
他們將較重的元素散佈在宇宙中
they seeded space with heavier elements,
使得行星的形成 成為可能
making possible the formation of planets,
最終 生命的形成
and ultimately, life.
大爆炸形成了物質和能量
Matter and energy were formed in the Big Bang.
還有
But that's not all.
創造了空間和時間
Space and time were created, too,
還有束縛所有物質的力量
and all the forces that bind matter together,
包括 重力
including gravity.
牛頓發現了一個數學定律
Isaac Newton discovered a mathematical law
可以形容重力的運作機制
that describes how gravity works.
他可以用它解釋行星間的運動
With that law, he could explain the motions of the planets.
100多年後
More than 100 years later,
威廉·赫歇爾 意識到 那還不是全部
William Herschel realized gravity could do much more.
約翰 你能保守秘密嗎
John, can you keep a secret?
可以 父親
Yes, Father.
我有了一個發現  還沒告訴過任何人
I've made a discovery and have yet to tell another soul.
地球上的地心引力
The gravity that holds us to the Earth--
同樣是牛頓發現的
the same gravity that Newton showed
將行星保持在軌道上的引力
keeps the planets in their orbits--
我發現
I've discovered
也同樣適用於 相隔遙遠的恆星們
that it also rules the distant stars.
爹  你咋知道的
Father... but how can you know this?
你能找到獅子座嗎
Can you find the constellation of the Lion?
在那
There.
幹得好
Well done.
你能找到
Can you now find the star
連接頭部和身體的那顆星嗎
that joins the Lion's head to his body?
那個
That one.
那其實是兩顆星
That star is really two stars
靠的很近 看上去就像一顆
so close together that they appear to be one.
我用望遠鏡觀察了很久
I've been watching them through my telescope
你出生很久前就開始了
since long before you were born.
他們非常緩慢的 圍繞相互移動
They dance around each other very slowly.
遠比行星繞恆星運動的慢
More slowly than any planet moves around the Sun.
我們今晚看到的許多星星
Many of the stars we see tonight,
可能大部分
perhaps most of them,
按照看不見的規律移動
dance with invisible partners.
萬有引力這個大帝國統治著所有的星球
Gravity's empire governs all the heavens.
1個世紀前
A century earlier,
艾薩克·牛頓備受困擾
Isaac Newton had been haunted
他也找不到引力的作用機制
by the same absence of a mechanism for gravity.
相距甚遠的物體 如何相互影響
How could distant bodies affect each other
不用接觸就相互影響
across empty space without actually touching?
這個他稱之為 超距作用 的問題困擾著他
This "action at a distance," as he called it, baffled him.
19世紀 邁克爾·法拉第（電學之父）發現
In the 19th century, Michael Faraday discovered
電學之父
我們被不可見的力場包圍
that we were surrounded by invisible fields of force
這解釋了引力的運作機制
that explained how gravity works.
蘋果和地球 並沒有發生接觸
The apple and the Earth don't touch each other,
但是他們之間的力場產生了接觸
but the fields between them do.
他想像引力產生的線
He imagined those lines of gravitational force
從每一個物體 向太空中輻射
radiating out into space from every massive body--
地球 月亮 太陽  所有的一切
the Earth, the Moon, the Sun, everything.
這就是那個困擾牛頓的問題
Here was the answer to that question
的答案
that had stumped Newton.
1985年 詹姆斯·克拉克·麥克斯韋
In 1865, James Clerk Maxwell translated Faraday's idea
把法拉第關於電磁場的理論
about fields of electricity and magnetism
轉化成了數學公式
into mathematical laws.
他發現這些磁場 電場都以波的形式在空間中移動
He discovered that these fields move through space in waves.
當他計算它們的移動速度時
When he calculated how fast they move,
結果是 光的速度
it turned out to be the speed of light.
我們才發現了  宇宙這個大掛毯上的線
We were beginning to discover the threads of the cosmic tapestry,
但是我們還無法 看出豐富的圖案
but we were not yet able to discern the rich pattern
時間 光 空間 重力
that time, light, space and gravity weave.
阿爾伯特·愛因斯坦 在柏林
As Albert Einstein worked in Berlin
研究他的引力理論時
on his theory of gravity,
牆上掛了這3位前輩的頭像
he kept the portraits of these three men before him.
他知道他的成就  建立在他們的基礎上
He knew he was standing on their shoulders.
多年前  少年時  他有過一個頓悟
Years before, as a teenager, he had an insight
如同前輩們的理論那般驚天動地
that was as Earth-shaking as any idea of theirs.
那年夏天
And it happened one summer
他在意大利遐想時的頓悟
while he was daydreaming in Italy.
1895年的夏天
In the summer of 1895,
他父親在德國的生意失敗
Einstein's father's business in Germany had failed,
全家搬到了意大利北部
and the family had moved here to northern Italy.
小愛因斯坦喜歡在這些路上散步
Young Einstein loved wandering these roads
讓他的思維隨意發散
and giving his mind free rein to explore.
這裏有著某些永恆的東西
There's something timeless about this place.
和愛因斯坦最初的遐想時相比
Nothing here has really changed
基本沒什麼變化
since the time of Einstein's early daydreams.
一天 他想到了光
One day, he began to think about light
還有光速
and how fast it travels.
日常生活中 我們總是測量物體
In everyday life, we always measure the speed
相對於其他物體的移動速度
of a moving object with respect to something else.
假設其他物體沒有移動
Something that's presumably not moving.
宇宙中的其他物體沒有運動
Something in the cosmos that's not in motion.
比方說  我的速度大約每小時10公里
For example, I'm moving about ten kilometers per hour
相對於地面而言
relative to the ground.
但我之前提過  大地也在運動
But as I mentioned earlier, the ground is moving.
地球的轉速超過每小時1600公里
Earth is turning at more than 1,600 kilometers per hour
在環日軌道上
while it orbits the Sun
速度超過每小時10萬公里
at more than 100,000 kilometers per hour.
並且太陽系在銀河系中運行
And the Sun is moving through the galaxy
約為每小時90萬公里
每小時50萬英里的速度
at a half a million miles per hour.
銀河系在宇宙中運行
And the Milky Way is moving through the universe
實際約為216萬公里
速度將近每小時150萬英里
at nearly one and a half million miles an hour.
宇宙中沒有不動的地方
There is no fixed place in the cosmos.
一切都在運動
All of nature is in motion.
對小愛因斯坦來說  也是很難想像出
It was hard even for the young Einstein
一個絕對的標準
to imagine some absolute standard
用來衡量所有這些相對的運動
to measure all those relative motions against.
就是這本書
This is the very book
啟發了少年愛因斯坦
that inspired Einstein as a young boy.
給了他一本書  改變了這個世界
Give a kid a book and you change the world.
某種程度上  改變了這個宇宙
In a way, even the universe.
看這裏  第一頁
Look at this-- the very first page,
它描述了令人驚訝的
it describes the astonishing speed
電流通過電線的速度
of electricity through wires
光穿過宇宙的速度
and light through space.
愛因斯坦記得他小時候從這本書裏學到的
Einstein remembered what he'd learned as a child from this book
或許 最初 就在這裏
and perhaps, for the first time, right here,
想像著這個世界將會如何
wondered what the world would look like
如果可以用光速運動
if you could travel at the speed of light.
愛因斯坦越想
The more Einstein thought about it,
越覺得困惑
the more troubled he became.
如果你想像以光速運動
If you imagine traveling at the speed of light,
各個方面都充滿了矛盾
paradoxes seem to pop up everywhere.
愛因斯坦驚訝的發現 如此眾多的
Einstein was shocked to realize that so much
即使是被最偉大的權威人士
of what had been uncritically accepted as truth
無條件接受的真理
by even the greatest authorities on the subject
竟是大錯特錯
was just plain wrong.
以高速運動時
When traveling at high speeds,
必須遵守一些特定的規則
there are certain rules which must be obeyed.
愛因斯坦稱之為 相對性原理
Einstein called these rules "The Principles of Relativity."
想像剛才那位呼嘯而過
Imagine that young woman who just blew past us
騎摩托的年輕女士
on the motorbike,
想像她騎車穿行
imagine she was riding her bike
在宇宙中
through the cosmos.
從移動的物體上發出的光
Light from a moving object travels
不論物體是靜止還是移動
at the same speed, no matter whether the object
速度都是一樣的
is at rest or in motion.
她的速度並不會增加光的速度
Her speed is not added to the speed of light.
從她的摩托車發出的光
The light from her motorbike
依然是光的速度
still travels at the speed of light.
大自然的諭旨
Nature commands,
汝不可超越光速
"Thou shalt not add my speed to the speed of light."
同樣 沒有物質
Also, no material object
傳播速度可以達到或者超過光速
can travel at or faster than the speed of light.
物理上 沒有什麼可以阻止你
There's nothing in physics that prevents you
隨心所欲地接近光的速度
from traveling as close to the speed of light as you like.
99.9%的光速 沒問題
99.9% of the speed of light is just fine,
但是無論你怎麼努力
but no matter how hard you try,
都無法得到 最後的那個百分點
you never gain that last decimal point.
以現實的邏輯一致性來說
For reality to be logically consistent,
必然存在一個宇宙速度極限
there must be a cosmic speed limit.
鞭子發出的聲音是因為
The crack of that whip is due to its tip
鞭頭的移動速度超過了聲速
moving faster than the speed of sound.
產生了衝擊波
It makes a shockwave,
例如這個在意大利鄉村的 一個小小的音爆
a mini sonic boom, in the Italian countryside.
打雷也是一樣的道理
A thunderclap works the same way,
還有超音速飛機掠過時的聲音
and so does the sound of a passing supersonic jet.
那為什麼光速
So why is the speed of light
比音速更難超越
any more a barrier than the speed of sound?
答案是 不僅僅光速
The answer is not just that light travels
比音速快100萬倍
about a million times faster than sound.
也因為 這不僅是一個工程學問題
And it's not merely an engineering problem,
像建造首架超音速飛機那種
like building the first supersonic jet.
光障
Instead, the light barrier
是自然的基本定律
is a fundamental law of nature,
就像萬有引力一樣基本
as basic as gravity.
愛因斯坦為這個世界設定了絕對的準則
Einstein found his absolute framework for the world,
這給了宇宙運動中的
this sturdy pillar among all the relative motions
所有相對運動強有力的支持
within the motions of the cosmos.
光速就是那麼快
Light travels just as fast,
無論光源移動的快慢
no matter how fast or slow its source is moving.
相對其他任何東西 光速是恆定的
Speed of light is constant, relative to everything else.
沒有什麼可以追上光
Nothing can ever catch up with light.
自然定律的偉大就是在於
The thing about the laws of nature
他們無懈可擊
is that they're unbreakable.
物理學家的工作就是發現這些定律
The job of physicists is to discover these commandments,
定律不隨文化的不同而改變
the ones that do not vary from culture to culture
也不隨時間而改變
or time to time
放之宇宙而皆准
and hold true throughout the cosmos.
這就是為何  如同愛因斯坦指出的
That's why, as Einstein showed,
接近光速時就出問題了
funny things happen close to the speed of light.
以接近光速的速度旅行
Traveling close to the speed of light
就像是長生不老藥
is kind of an elixir of life
我們的生物鐘慢下來
because your biological clock slows down
相對於其他人來說
relative to those you leave behind.
這種現象或許可以為我們人類
This phenomenon may provide us humans,
只能活1個世紀左右的人類
who only live for a century or so,
提供一個可行的恆星間旅行的方案
a practical means to travel to the stars,
時空魔法大戲
where the magic show of spacetime
精彩紛呈
really gets crazy.
19世紀的天文學家 威廉·赫歇爾
The 19th-century astronomer William Herschel
喜歡和他的兒子約翰
loved to share the wonders of the universe
分享宇宙中的奇跡
with his son John.
我有個朋友 一個很聰明的傢伙
I once had a friend, very clever fellow,
天文學家 也是裏茲的牧師
an astronomer and a parson at Leeds,
叫 約翰·米切爾
by the name of John Michell.
你還是嬰兒時 他就過世了
Poor man died when you were a babe,
願他安息
God rest his soul.
他堅信有些星星
He held that some stars
雖然看不到
are invisible.
卻確實存在 但是我們永遠無法看到
They really exist, but we shall never see them.
米切爾叫他們 「暗星」
"Dark stars," Michell called them.
恕我直言 父親
With all due respect, Father,
你的朋友肯定弄錯了
surely your friend was mistaken.
如果沒人能看到
If no one can see them,
我們怎麼能知道它們確實存在
then how can we possibly know they exist?
你看到留下腳印的人了嗎
Did you see the man who left those footprints, John?
沒 怎麼了
Why, no, Father.
我沒看到
I did not.
但你知道他們確實存在 不是嗎
But do you know that he exists?
約翰 米切爾是最偉大的科學家之一
John Michell is one of the greatest scientists
你可能從沒聽說過
you've probably never heard of.
他生活工作於18世紀的英格蘭
He lived and worked in England in the 18th century.
現在也沒有他的畫像存世
If he ever sat for a portrait, it no longer exists.
有人曾經形容他
He was once described by an acquaintance
胖胖的黝黑小矮人
as "a short little man, of black complexion, and fat."
米切爾設想一個巨大的恆星
Michell imagined a star so big,
質量巨大到 即使光線
so massive, that nothing, not even light,
也無法逃離它的重力吸引
could escape its gravitational grip.
你能找到暗星嗎
Can you find the dark star?
暗星主要由超中性子構成 並通過暗物質和正物質的湮滅釋放能量
你無法用肉眼直接看見它
You can't see it with your eyes, not directly,
但在宇宙這個沙灘上
but it may leave a kind of footprint
它可能留下某種足跡
on the cosmic shore.
米切爾認為因為他們巨大的引力
Michell realized that we might be able to detect
使得我們或許可以偵測到他們
some of these dark stars because of their extreme gravity.
如果一個暗星 碰巧伴隨著一個
If one happened to be near
稍小些 會發光的星星
a smaller, luminous companion star,
那顆星星以緊密的軌道
that star would appear to travel in a tight orbit
環繞著 看不見的東西運行
around nothing.
即使我們看不到
Even though we can't see it,
我們也知道 有個質量超級巨大的
we know something with a lot of mass
東西在那裏
has to be right there.
暗星
A dark star,
或者叫 黑洞
or what today we call a black hole.
黑洞長什麼樣子
What does a black hole look like
它的裏面是什麼樣子的
and what would it be like inside?
我們以後會提到  但是首先
We'll get there, but first,
讓我們先在我的家鄉稍作休息
let's make a pit stop in my hometown,
紐約
New York City,
這地方在我來看
where it's always seemed to me
所有的一切都在不停地運動
that everything is in constant motion.
我在這裏住了大半輩子
I've lived here most of my life.
總有新鮮事物
There's always something new to see.
但有一樣從來不變 重力
But one thing never changes-- gravity.
重力在過去的45億年間
Gravity on Earth has been the same
一直保持不變
for the past four and a half billion years.
如果 今天 我們可以改變它
But what if, today, we could alter it?
重力受時空影響
Gravity is a distortion
會發生畸變
in the shape of spacetime
如同愛因斯坦提出的理論
as Einstein showed.
空間可以膨脹和收縮
Space can expand and contract
甚至無限彎曲
and warp without limit.
如果地球的體積和密度
If the Earth's size or density
有細微的不同
were even a little different,
它的重力也會不同
its gravity would be, too.
有無限的可能性
There's an infinite range of possibilities.
紐約人在這裏感受到的
New Yorkers feel right at home
重力單位
in the gravitational pull of the Earth,
我們稱為 1g
called "one g."
假設我們取消一條街上的重力
Suppose we turn off the gravity on one of its streets.
運動中的人和物體
People and objects that were already in motion
就會向上飛去
are launched into flight.
如果我把重力加大到
Now what if I turn the gravity up
比方說 8或者9g
to, say, eight or nine g's?
和諧起見
Out of compassion,
把人拿開
let's evacuate the area.
這個重力和戰鬥機飛行員
This is about the same g-force
高速轉彎時承受的重力相當
that a fighter pilot in a high-speed turn would feel.
幾分鐘內 還不會使你受傷
A few minutes of this wouldn't hurt you,
但是絕不會舒服
but it wouldn't be comfortable.
在10萬g時
At 100,000 g's,
消防栓也被自身的重量
even fire hydrants become crushed
壓扁了
by their own enormous weight.
而當達到幾百萬g
But at millions of g's,
光線也會被拉彎
even light bows to gravity.
光線依然保持恆速
The light still moves at its constant speed,
但它無法逃逸
but it cannot escape.
米切爾說的暗星
Michell's dark star...
我們稱為黑洞
our black hole.
最近的一個 或許比想像的要近
And the nearest one may be closer than you think.
不是每個恆星都會變成黑洞
Not every star can become a black hole.
只有千分之一的質量足夠大
Only about one in a thousand is massive enough.
最近的一個 可能距離地球不到100光年
The nearest one could be within 100 light years of Earth.
黑洞不是科幻小說裏的宇宙吸塵器
Black holes aren't the mythic cosmic vacuum cleaners of science fiction.
它們不會到處吞噬
They don't go around gobbling up unsuspecting worlds.
你得去找它們
You've got to come to them.
但是如果你去了
But if you do,
可就是有去無回
it might be the last thing you ever see.
剛才那是我們在抵抗上百萬g的重力
That was us resisting a few million g's of gravity.
別忘了 那傢伙可以吞噬光線
Don't forget, that thing swallows light.
我們不能靠的太近
We'll keep our distance.
當巨大的恆星消耗完它們的核燃料
When giant stars exhaust their nuclear fuel,
他們不再保持高溫
they can no longer stay hot enough
以抵消自身向內的引力
to fend off the inward pull of their own gravity.
質量最大的恆星塌陷
The most massive stars collapse into darkness,
沒有光亮 只留下重力
leaving only their gravity behind.
這個黑洞將一個超巨星的萎縮的屍體
This black hole enshrouds the shrunken corpse
隱藏其中
of a supergiant star.
恆星本身可能萎縮到
The star itself has shriveled into something
比黑洞還小
even smaller than this darkness,
只有64公里寬
only 64 kilometers wide.
這是發現的第一個黑洞
This is the first black hole ever discovered--
天鵝座X-1
Cygnus X-1.
我們在地球上是怎麼發現
How did we on Earth ever find something
這麼小 這麼暗 這麼遠的 東西
so small and dark and far away?
我們通過另一種光 X光
We looked at it in another kind of light. X-rays.
X光中 我們看不到藍色的星星了
In X-ray light, we lost sight of the blue star
因為它的表面溫度只有微溫的3萬度
because its surface is a tepid 30,000 degrees.
而黑洞周圍的氣體圓盤
But the disk of gas around the black hole
在X光中發出耀眼的光芒 溫度高達1億度
glowed brilliantly in X-rays at 100 million degrees.
如同威廉·赫歇爾所發現的
As William Herschel discovered,
很多恆星都有親密的小夥伴  組成聯星系統
many stars have close companions forming a binary star system.
但如果其中一個異常巨大
But if one member of such a pair is enormous
另一個比較小
and the other is compact,
小的這個可以吞噬它兄弟的
the smaller star can drain and consume the atmosphere
大氣層
of its larger sibling.
這種神經病關係可以持續幾百萬年
This neurotic relationship can last for millions of years.
較大恆星的大氣層被抽到熾熱耀眼的吸積盤上
The atmosphere of the larger star was being siphoned onto
吸積盤不停自轉
a glowing hot accretion disk that revolves around
並且漩渦式的進入黑洞
and spirals into a black hole.
勢不可擋的重力不斷加速藍色星星的氣體
The overwhelming gravity was accelerating the blue star's gas
將其捲入死亡漩渦
into a death spiral,
跨過時空的界限
crossing the spacetime boundary,
一去不復返
never to be seen again.
這至關重要的界限將黑洞
The fateful boundary that separates a black hole
與宇宙的其他部分隔離開  被稱為 事件視界
from the rest of the universe is called an event horizon.
在我們看來 吸積盤中的物質
From our point of view, the substance in the disk
在靠近視界時慢下來
slows down as it approaches the event horizon,
但絕不接觸它
never quite reaching it.
如果你站在大氣漩渦上
But if you were riding on that spiraling gas--
我並不建議這麼做
and I don't advise it--
幾秒鐘就會越過事件視界
you would sail past the event horizon in a matter of seconds
進入到 從沒人回來的 未知國度
into the undiscovered country from which no traveler returns.
我們搜索了幾十個星系的中心
We have searched the hearts of dozens of galaxies,
在每個裏面都能找到 一個質量超級大的黑洞
and in every case, we have found a super-massive black hole.
我們的銀河系也不例外
Our own galaxy is no exception.
最靠近銀河系中心的恆星運動的速度
The stars nearest the center of our galaxy whip around
超過每小時4千萬公里
at more than 40 million kilometers an hour.
他們怎麼會運動的這麼快
What could make them move so fast?
唯一合理的解釋是
The only logical explanation
銀河系中央存在著
is that something with the mass
質量等於4百萬個太陽的物體
of four million suns lies at the center.
這4百萬個太陽發出的光去哪裏了
So where's the blazing light of four million suns?
既然我們看不見
Since we can't see it,
它一定是被禁錮在黑洞裏了
it must be imprisoned inside a black hole.
地球離得很遠 很安全
Earth is far enough away to be perfectly safe.
其他的世界或許沒有這麼幸運
Other worlds might not be so lucky.
如果你能穿過事件視界
If you somehow survived the perilous journey
卻還活著
across the event horizon,
你可以回頭看
you'd be able to look back out
宇宙的整部未來史都會
and see the entire future history of the universe
展現在你眼前
unfold before your eyes.
怎麼會的
How?
因為 時空受到
Because when spacetime is warped
黑洞的極度重力影響而扭曲
by the extreme gravity of a black hole,
時間被拉伸至極致
time is stretched to the limit.
但你面前會是何種景象呢
But what would be in front of you?
我提前警告你
Before we go there, I should warn you
我們說的是未經涉足過的科學領域
that we're entering uncharted scientific territory.
那裏可能有我們未知的物理定律
For all we know, there may be undiscovered laws of physics
支配著黑洞中央的事情
that govern events at the center of a black hole.
在下一個愛因斯坦出現前
But until the next Einstein comes along,
我們來做個思想實驗吧
let's perform a thought experiment.
18世紀的約翰 米切爾
That's how John Michell first imagined dark stars
就是靠它想像出 暗星
in the 18th century,
愛因斯坦也是這麼想出他的...
and how Einstein conceived of his theory of rela...
父親 你相信有鬼魂嗎
Father, do you believe in ghosts?
我不信有 人類的鬼魂
Oh, no, not in the human kind of ghosts.
完全不信
No, not at all.
但是 向上看 兒子
But look up, my boy,
滿天都是鬼魂
and see a sky full of them.
你如果去過黑洞還能活著回來
If you could survive the trip into a black hole,
你可能會發現
you might emerge in another place
我們宇宙中的其他時間和空間
and time in our own universe,
先不提 相對論的第一條戒律
circumventing the first commandment of relativity...
汝不可超越光速
thou shalt not travel faster than light.
太空中沒有什麼速度可以比光速快
Nothing can move through space faster than light.
但太空並不空曠
But space is not mere emptiness.
空間可以延伸 收縮  被扭曲
Its properties can stretch and shrink and can be deformed.
那樣的話 時間也會被扭曲
And when that happens, time is deformed, too.
愛因斯坦發現 空間和時間 只是
Einstein discovered that spaceand time are just two aspects
一個事物的兩個方面  時空
of the same thing, spacetime.
時空本身可以被任意彎曲
Spacetime itself can deform enough
用任意速度帶你去任意地方
to carry you anywhere at any speed.
黑洞可能是不同宇宙間的隧道
Black holes may very well be tunnels through the universe.
通過這種星際間的交通系統 你可以
On this intergalactic subway system, you could travel
達到時空的最遠端
to the farthest reaches of spacetime,
或許其他更驚人的地方
or you might arrive in someplace even more amazing.
或許是個完全不一樣的宇宙
We might find ourselves in an altogether different universe.
但是一個黑洞怎麼能容納整個宇宙
But how can a whole universe fit inside of a black hole,
黑洞只是我們宇宙中的很小一部分
which is only a small part of our universe?
這又是一個時空變出的戲法
It's another magic trick of spacetime.
黑洞無與倫比的引力
The phenomenal gravity of a black hole
可以將整個宇宙的空間扭曲並塞進去
can warp the space of an entire universe inside it.
我們現在受到的引力 或許很強
Our local gravity might be a drag to us,
但卻無法和
but it's really feeble compared
萎縮恆星內部的引力 相提並論
with what goes on inside a collapsed star.
據我們所知
As far as we know,
當超大恆星萎縮成黑洞時
when a giant star collapses to make a black hole,
中心產生極大的密度和壓力
the extreme density and pressure at the center
如同誕生宇宙的大爆炸
mimic the Big Bang, which gave rise to our universe.
於是黑洞內誕生了一個宇宙
And a universe inside a black hole
這宇宙可能會產生它自己的黑洞
might give rise to its own black holes.
這些黑洞 又會產生其他的宇宙
And those could lead to other universes.
或許我們的宇宙就是如此
Maybe that's how our cosmos came to be.
眾所周知
For all we know,
如果你想知道黑洞裏面有什麼
if you want to see what it's like inside a black hole,
只要看看四周
just look around you.
威廉·赫歇爾發現了 太陽
William Herschel went on to discover that the sun
帶著它的行星們 在銀河系中運行
and its planets are moving through the Milky Way.
他的兒子有什麼成就呢
And whatever became of his son John?
他成為了一位偉大的科學家
He grew up to become a great scientist.
在他父親的基礎上 他所得出的外太空觀測結果
His deep-space observations built on those of his father
成為了星系標準目錄的依據
to become the basis for the standard catalog of galaxies
沿用至今
we use today.
當威廉身體不好時  約翰陪著他
When William was in failing health, John stayed with him
在望遠鏡旁 度過長夜
through the long nights at his telescope
幫他觀測恆星
to help him sweep the stars.
父親過世後 約翰寫下墓誌銘
And when his father died, John wrote his epitaph...
他推倒天堂的圍牆
"He broke through the walls of heaven."
約翰經常緬懷
John often reminisced
與他父親度過的那些夏日夜晚
about those summer nights with his father.
這或許就是為何 他要尋找保存過去的方法
Maybe that's why he sought a way to preserve the past.
約翰 赫歇爾 是一種展現形式的時間旅行的
John Herschel was one of the founders
創始人之一
of a new form of time travel,
一種保留光線和記憶的辦法
a means to capture light and memories.
他為它選擇了一個名字
He actually coined a word for it,
攝影
photography.
你這麼想
When you think about it,
攝影是時間旅行的一種形式
photography is a form of time travel.
幾百年前的人注視著我們
This man is staring at us from across the centuries...
光線勾勒出的鬼魂
a ghost preserved by light.
不難想像 在不遠的未來
It's not hard to imagine that in the near future,
我們可以保留過去
we'll be able to capture the past
以三維立體的形式
in all three dimensions.
我們可以走進一段記憶
We'll be able to step inside a memory.
或許不能回到過去的時間
It may not be possible to travel backward in time,
但可能 有一天 可以將過去帶來現在
but perhaps, one day, we can bring the past to us.
這是我過去的一刻
Here's a moment from my past.
就像約翰赫歇爾
Like John Herschel,
我記得幼年的我
I'm remembering a younger version of myself.
1975年12月20號
December 20, 1975.
紐約的一個雪天
A snowy day in Ithaca, New York.
生命旅程的一個拐點
A branchpoint on the road that brought me
讓我有機會站在這裏
to this moment with you.
那天我遇到了卡爾·塞根
It was the day I met Carl Sagan.
就如同天空中那些星星的鬼魂
Reminds me of those ghost stars in the sky...
即使已經消亡 但星光依然照耀我們
you know, the ones that still shine their light upon us long after they're gone.
中文翻譯：@SaltyEggPain
原字幕取自射手 由HDWinG字幕組修正 請勿去掉製作者信息